<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The boke of nurture for men, seruauntes, and chyldren]</title>
            <author>Rhodes, Hugh, fl. 1550.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S498</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22528056</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22528056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1756:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The boke of nurture for men, seruauntes, and chyldren]</title>
                  <author>Rhodes, Hugh, fl. 1550.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1570]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Rhodes by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all except signatures A₂₊A₃.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Social life and customs --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25593:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25593:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
            <p>FIrſt ye thuſt be diligent to know your Maſters plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and to know the order, &amp; cuſtome of his houſe. For diuers maiſters are of ſundry conditions &amp; appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tites. And if thou be admitted in any office as Buttry, or Pantry, in ſome places they are all one. Then take an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tory of all ſuch thinges as ye take charge of, how it is ſpent. For it pleaſeth a maiſter to haue a true reckening, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in your office of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pantry ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your bread be chipped &amp; ſquared, &amp; note how much ye ſpend in one day. Alſo ſe your napry clene, &amp; ſort euery thig by it ſelf, the clene fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foul &amp; kepe your houſe of office clene, &amp; all that belongeth to it. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your maſter wil go to his meate, take a towel about your neck, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take a cupbord cloth, a baſin &amp; an ewer, &amp; a towell to aray your cupborde, then couer your table, &amp; ſet on ſalt, brede &amp; trenchours, the ſalt before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread, &amp; tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chours before the ſalt, &amp; ſet your napkins &amp; ſpones on the cupbord redy, &amp; lay euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chour and napkin and a ſpone: &amp; if ye haue mo meſſes then one at your maſters ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble conſider what degre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons are of, &amp; thereafter you may ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet down euery thig at that meſſe as before, except your karuing kniues. If there be many ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or yome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet on bread, ſalt, tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chours, ſpones, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter they be ſet, or els after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the houſe. Alſo ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do vſe to ſet before euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lofe of bread &amp; his cup, &amp; ſome vſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, thus muſt you haue reſpect to the cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your houſe, &amp; in ſome places it is vſe to ſet drink &amp; a lofe or two. In ſome places the keruer dooth vſe to ſewe and ſet downe and goeth before the courſe, and beareth no diſhe, and in ſome place, he beareth the firſte diſhe, and maketh obeyſaunce to his Mayſter, and ſetteth it down couered before the degre of a Knight, or els not vſed, &amp; take of the couers &amp; ſet them by. Alſo the karuer hath authoritie to carue to all at his maſters mes in ſpecial, alſo vnto other that ſit ioyning by them if he liſt, alſo ye haue voyders in a redines to auoid the morſels that they do leane on their
<pb facs="tcp:25593:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->trenchours. Then with your trenchour knife take of ſuch fragments and put them in your voyder, and ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again. And whether youre ſoueraign haue trenchours or bread voyd the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or twiſe, ſpecialy whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are wet, or geue him clean, and as ye ſe men leaue eating of the firſt and ſecond diſh: ſo auoyd them from the table. And then if that ſo bee ye haue any more courſes then one or two: ye may make the more haſt in voyding, and euer let one diſh or two ſtand till the next courſe, and then take vp all and ſet downe freſhe and cleane voyders withall, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be to ful or ye empty them, and then ſet cleane againe and looke what ſauce is ordeined for anye meat voyde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſauce therof when ye take away the meate. And at the degree of a knight ye may ſet down your cup, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and lift of the couer and ſet it on again, and when he liſteth to drink and taketh of the couer: take the couer in thy hand and ſet it on again, and when he hath dronken looke the cup of wine or ale be not empty, but often renu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. Alſo the karuer ſhall breake his diſh before his maſter or at ſide Cupbord with cleane kniues, and ſe there be no lack of bread nor ale, and when men haue wel eaten, and do beginne to ware wery of eating, or if ye perceyue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countenaunce of youre mayſter when ye ſhall take vp the meat and voyde the table: begin at the loweſt meaſe, take away your ſpones if there be any, howbeit ye may auoyd them, after brothes and bake meates are paſt. Then take away your voiders and then your diſhes of meate as they were ſet down ſo take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in order and then ſet down cheeſe or fruites, and that ended auoid your cheſe &amp; fruits and couer your cup, Ale or Wine, firſt auoyd the Ale, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Wine, then ſet on a broad voyder and put therein the ſmall peces of bread and ſmall cromes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trenchours and napkins, and with your trenchour knife or napkin make cleane the table, then ſet away your bread whole and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo your voyder, and then take vp the ſalt and make obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:25593:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->mark if your maiſter vſe to waſhe at the table, or ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, if he be at the table caſt a clene towel vpon your table cloth &amp; ſet down youre baſin and ewer before youre ſoueraigne, and take the ewer in your hand and geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> water, then auoyd your baſin and ewer and folde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borde cloth together with your towell therin, and ſo take them of the borde. And when your ſoueraigne ſhall waſhe: ſet youre towel on the left hand of him, and the water before you at ſupper or dinner, if it be to bedward ſet vp your ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſin &amp; your towel on the cupbord againe. And if your maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wil haue any conceits after diner, as Apples, Nuts or creame, then lay forth a towel on the borde, and ſet thero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lofe or two, ſe that ye haue trenchours and ſpoones in a redines if nede require, and then ſerue forth your maſter well, and ſo take it vp againe with a voyder.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The ordering of your Maiſters chamber at night to bedward.</p>
               <p>ARay your cupborde with a cupborde cloth with your baſin and ewer, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle light and towel, if ye haue help ſet one to beare a Torch, or ſome other light before &amp; another felow to beare a Towel for youre table w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bread as thou ſeeſt nede. And if you haue banket diſhes whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, as frutes put in ſondry diſhes and all other con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fections &amp; conceites of ſpicery, alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſhes are em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty auoid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table, if youre ſoueraine be a Knight or Squier: ſet down your diſhes couered and your cup al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And if your ſoueraigne be not ſet at the table let youre diſhes ſtand couered til he be ſet, and when he is ſet: then take away the voiders. And when your maiſter ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to bedward ſe that ye haue fire &amp; candle ſufficient, &amp; ſe ye haue cleane water in at night and in the morning, and if your maiſter ly in freſhe ſheetes dry of the dankiſhenes by the fire. And if he lie in a ſtraunge place, ſe his ſheetes be
<pb facs="tcp:25593:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->cleane &amp; ſweet, and then folde down his bed, and warme his night kerchef, and ſe his houſe of office be cleane, and help of his clothing and draw the curtaines, &amp; make ſure the fire &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, &amp; auoyd the dogs &amp; ſhut all the dores. And in the euening or in the mornig your maſter being alone if ye haue any thinge to ſay to him, then is good layſer &amp; time to know his pleaſure. In the morning if it be colde make a fire &amp; haue in clene water, &amp; bring him his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cote warme with his Doublet and all his Apparel clene bruſhed, &amp; his ſhoes made cleane, &amp; help to aray him, trus his points, ſtrike vp his hoſen clene, and ſe all thing clene &amp; clenly about him, giue him good attendaunce, &amp; in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall among ſtraungers, for attendaunce doth pleſe maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters very wel. Thus doinge with diligence God wil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to honour and good fortune,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ Here foloweth the booke of Nurtur and of good maners, for Man and Childe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>AL ye that woold lerne, and then wold be called wiſe</l>
                  <l>Obedience lerne in youth, in age it wil auoyd vice</l>
                  <l>I am blind in Poets art, therof I can no ſkill,</l>
                  <l>Al eloquence I put a part, and folow mine own wil,</l>
                  <l>Corrupt in ſpeech my breues and longs to know:</l>
                  <l>Borne and bred in Deuonſhire, my termes wil wel ſhow</l>
                  <l>Take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt and leaue the worſt, of truth I meane none il</l>
                  <l>If the mater be not curious, thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is good mark it well</l>
                  <l>Pardon I aſk if I offend, thus boldly for to write</l>
                  <l>To maſter or ſeruant (young &amp; olde) I do my ſelf ſubmit</l>
                  <l>I would reform both youth and age, if any thing be amis</l>
                  <l>To you wil I ſhew my minde, reforme ye where nede is</l>
                  <l>All that haue you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g people, good maners ſet them to learn</l>
                  <l>To their elders w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle condicto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let do nor ſay no harm</l>
                  <l>If they do il, wiſe men may report their Parents ſone</l>
                  <l>How ſhold they teach other good, belike the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none</l>
                  <l>I good Father maketh good Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> win</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:25593:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
